Guide to the Margaret Morse Nice papers, 1917-1968
Nice, Margaret Morse papers, 1917-1968
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Margaret Morse Nice papers, 1917-1968
2993
Margaret Morse Nice, 1883-1974.
6.6 cubic ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, subject files, reports, pictures, photographs, drawings, pamphlets.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Personal correspondence and manuscripts, and professional papers including subject files, correspondence, reports and manuscripts of articles related to Margaret Morse Nice's term as associate editor of Bird Banding and of the Wilson Bulletin; manuscripts for articles, lectures, radio broadcasts, etc. on ornithology; pictures and photographs; notes and drawings; printed pamphlets; and abstracts of writings by others.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Margaret Morse Nice was an ornithologist.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Personal correspondence and manuscripts, and professional papers including subject files, correspondence, reports and manuscripts of articles related to Margaret Morse Nice's term as associate editor of Bird Banding and of the Wilson Bulletin; manuscripts for articles, lectures, radio broadcasts, etc. on ornithology; pictures and photographs; notes and drawings; printed pamphlets; and abstracts of writings by others. Correspondents include Olin Sewall Pettingill, Josselyn Van Tyne, Thomas Calderwood Stephens, Althea Rosina Sherman, and Winnifred Smith.
Also, reprints of articles by Margaret Morse Nice, 1924-1946, on ornithological topics
PARTIAL INDEX TO PERSONAL CORRESPONDENCE IN BOX 1
Letters (some in German or French) from European ornithologists, mainly 1945-1949, dealing in part with ornithological subjects, but also discussing hardships undergone during and after World War II and mentioning family affairs; some have family photographs attached. From the following countries:
Czechoslovakia
1947
Jan. 6, 21
1948
Jan. 8, 14; Aug. 4; Nov. 1 (?)
Hungary
1946
Mar. 18; Apr. 15; May 8; July 5
1947
Jan. 8, 14; Aug. 4; Nov. 1 (?)
1948
Apr. 30; Feb. 8; Oct. 14
1949
Feb. 8
Netherlands (some typed on both sides of paper--somewhat illegible)
1945
June 23; Sept. 6; Nov. 7; Dec. 5
1946
Jan. 4, 6; Feb. 13, 26; May 27; July 20; Sept. 1; Dec. 28
1947
Mar. 17; June 29
1949
Oct. 10
Germany--numerous, including:
G. Diesselhorst, Emmering, Bavaria
1950
Feb. 28 (in German)
O. Koehler, Freiburg, Baden
1946
Aug. 19 (from Denmark)
1947
Jan. 30; Feb. 28; Mar. 4; Apr. 24, May 10; July 21; Nov. 13
1948
Aug. 22; Sept. 17, 21; Dec. 30
1949
Feb. 28; May 24; Sept. 8 (letter in poor condition)
Hanna and Gerd Krause
1949
Apr. 14; May 12
Konrad and Margaretha Lorenz
Handwritten from KL to MMN:
1935
Sept. 19
1936
Mar. 12
1937
Sept. 13
1938
Jan. 28; July 18; Nov. 9
Carbon copy, MMN to KL:
1938
Oct. 5
1939
Jan. 29
Copy of typed letter from KL to MMN:
1939
Feb. 14
Handwritten from Margaretha:
1946
Aug. 21
1947
Nov. 26
1950
Feb. 1
Typed from KL to MMN:
1949
May 10--very interesting
Copy of typed letter from KL to Prof. ? Craig:
1949
Sept. 2
References to Konrad Lorenz in letters from other German ornithologists
1950
Jan. 15; Feb. 3
Erwin Stresemann, German Ornithological Society, Berlin (one includes photo of him and his wife Vesta)
1945?
1946
numerous
1947
1948
1949
Apr. 19
Brussels, Brussels (in French)
1946
Sept. 24
1947
May 21
Switzerland, Geneva (in French)
1947
Jan. 12
United Kingdom
?, Richdale, Dunedin, Scotland
1946
Sept. 4; Nov. 2
1948
Dec. 3
A. W. Boyd, Cheshire
1946
Oct. 13
1947
Jan. 11; Nov. 12
Earlier letters from William Boyd, U. of Glasgow (same person?)
1917
Aug. 25
1925
Apr. 20; Dec. 5
North America (incomplete)
Clara N. Bates, Oklahoma City
1926
July 11
1927
Spring
Milam B Cater, Millboro, Virginia
1949
Feb. 24; Mar. 16; June 12
Joseph J. Hickey
1950
Feb. 17; perhaps others
Alla R. Phillips
1949
Jan. 26; Mar. 7, 29; May 12
W.E. Schantz
1937
(perhaps earlier)
1938
1939
(perhaps later)
Rose S. Taylor, Sioux City, Iowa (Mrs. H.S. Taylor)
1924
July 16
1929
Oct. 17 (at Berkeley); Dec. 28 (Des Moines)
1931
Nov. 17 (Berkeley)
1936
Sept. 30
Other North American ornithologists include Althea R. Sherman (in Box 5, Folder 1) and Edward R. Ford of Michigan. There are also a number of ornithological letters, mostly from women friends whose surnames are not mostly not given: Ruth ? of Arkansas, Amelia ? of Nashville, Dorothy ? of Indianapolis, Josephine Michener of Pasadena, Florence M?, and Anne ? of Arkansas.
There is also a carbon copy of a typed letter to President Harry Truman from June 28, 1948, regarding persecution of American anti-Fascist groups, along with carbons of letters MMN wrote to Chicago newspapers on various ornithological and/or political issues.
Canada
Louise deR. (?), Rutherglen, Ontario
1949
July 27; Aug. 8; Sept. 2, 12
Doris Spiers, Pickering, Ontario
1949
Aug. 10
Mexico
1947
Apr. 2; June 17
SUBJECTS
Names:
Nice, Margaret Morse, b. 1883.; Pettingill, Olin Sewall, 1907-; Sherman, Althea R. (Althea Rosina), 1853-1943.; Stephens, T.C. (Thomas Calderwood), 1876-1948.; Van Tyne, Josselyn, 1902-1957.; Smith, Winnifred.
Titles:
Bird banding.; Wilson bulletin.
Subjects:
Women authors.; Ornithologists--United States.; Ornithology--United States.
Form and Genre Terms:
Articles.; Lectures.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Personal papers
Correspondence
Boxes 1-2, 19
Non-ornithological manuscripts
Box 3
Series II. Professional papers
Associate editor, Bird Banding
Boxes 3-5
Associate editor, Wilson Bulletin
Boxes 5-6
Scholarly manuscripts
Boxes 6-18
Series III. Reprints
Box 20
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Personal papers
  - Correspondence
    - Personal Correspondence, 1917-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1946- May 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Personal Correspondence, May 1946-Dec. 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Personal Correspondence, Apr. 1947-Nov. 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Personal Correspondence, Jan. 1947-Mar. 1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Personal Correspondence, Aug.-Nov. 1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Personal Correspondence, Jan. 1948-June 1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Personal Correspondence, July 1948-Dec. 1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Personal Correspondence, June 1949-Mar. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Personal Correspondence, Mar. 1949-May 1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Personal Correspondence, June 1949-Sept. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Personal Correspondence, Oct. 1949-Dec. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Personal Correspondence, Jan. 1950-Feb. 1950 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Personal Correspondence, Mar. 1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Personal Correspondence, Apr. 1950-Dec. 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Personal Correspondence, Aug. 1950-Dec. 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1952-Mar. 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Personal Correspondence, Mar. 1952-Apr. 1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Personal Correspondence, May 1952-Aug. 1952 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Personal Correspondence, Aug. 1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Personal Correspondence, Sept. 1952-Oct. 1952 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Personal Correspondence, Oct. 1952-Dec. 1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Personal Correspondence, Jan. 1953-June 1953 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Personal Correspondence, June 1953-Dec. 1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Personal Correspondence, Jan. 1954-Apr. 1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Personal Correspondence, May 1954-Dec. 1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Personal Correspondence, Jan. 1955-Mar. 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Personal Correspondence, Apr. 1956-Aug. 1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Personal Correspondence, Apr. 1960-June 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Personal Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Additional Correspondence, 1946-1967 (Box 19)
  - Non-ornithological manuscripts
    - "Fairy Tales from Celtic Lands. Selected and Adapted by Margaret Morse Nice" (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Non-ornithological activities Defense of National Parks and Monument (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Photographs of some foreign ornithologists (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Fire-ants and pesticides (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Series II. Professional papers
  - Associate editor, Bird Banding
    - Letters to the Editor of Bird Banding (Dove letter) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bird Banding correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Bird Banding correspondence, 1941-1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bird Banding correspondence, 1951-Mar. 1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Bird Banding correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Bird Banding correspondence, 1955-Dec. 1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Bird Banding correspondence, Jan. 1957-1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Recent literature, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Recent literature, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Recent literature, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Recent literature, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Recent literature, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Recent literature, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Recent literature, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Recent literature, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Recent literature, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Recent literature, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Recent literature, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Recent literature, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Recent literature, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Recent literature, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Recent literature, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Recent literature, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Recent literature, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Recent literature, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Recent literature, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Recent literature, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Recent literature, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Recent literature, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Recent literature, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Recent literature, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Recent literature, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Recent literature, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Recent Literature, Oct. 1941 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Recent Literature, Jan. 1942 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Recent Literature, Apr. 1942 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Recent Literature, July 1942 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Recent Literature, Oct. 1942 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, 1937-1942 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, Jan.-Apr. 1946 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, July-Oct. 1946 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, Jan. 1947 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, Feb.-Dec. 1947 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, Jan.-Apr. 1948 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Misc. articles published in Bird Banding (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Misc. articles published in Bird Banding (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, July 1948-Dec. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, Oct. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, July & Oct. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, Jan. & Apr. 1949 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, Apr. 1952 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, July 1952-Dec. 1952 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, Jan. 1953 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, Apr. 1953 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, July 1953 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, Oct. 1953 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Bird Banding book reviews, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Associate editor, Wilson Bulletin
    - Althea Sherman letters, 1921-1932, draft notes for article (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Wilson Bulletin correspondence, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Wilson Bulletin correspondence, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Wilson Bulletin correspondence, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Wilson Bulletin correspondence, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Wilson Bulletin correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Wilson Bulletin articles (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Wilson Bulletin correspondence, 1942-1949 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Wilson Bulletin correspondence, 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Wilson Bulletin correspondence, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Wilson Bulletin correspondence, 1955-1961, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Wilson Bulletin editing materials (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Vultures - incubation period (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Schantz on catbirds, 1936-1940 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Wood Pewee sketches (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - The aftermath of the Second World War re: European relief (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - American Aid to European Ornithologists (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Chicago region -- spring warbler surveys (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Scholarly manuscripts
    - Correspondence with other organizations: A (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with other organizations: B-D (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with other organizations: F-J (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with other organizations: L-M (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence with other organizations: N-O (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with other organizations: P-W (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence with other organizations: Z (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Song Sparrow- work sheets from observations (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Birds of Oklahoma (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Appendix material- Cowbirds, Vol. 1 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - General outlines for Chapter 1, Vol. 1 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Song Sparrow- general outline, early material Chapters V, X, Vol. 1 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Song Sparrow- chapter subjects, Vol. 1 Behavior of the Song Sparrow (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Behavior of the Song Sparrow
      - Table of Contents and Foreword (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Chapter I (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Chapter II (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Chapter III (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Chapter IV & V (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Chapter VI (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Chapter VII (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Chapter VIII (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Chapter IX & X (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Chapter XI (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Chapter XII (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Chapter XIII (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Chapter XIV (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Chapter XV (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Chapter XVI (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Chapter XVII (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - Chapter XVIII (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - Chapter XIX (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - Chapter XX (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - Chapter XXI (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - Chapter XXII (Box 7, Folder 21)
      - Table of Appendix (1) (Box 7, Folder 22)
      - Table of Appendix (2) (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - Bibliography (1) (Box 7, Folder 24)
      - Bibliography (2) (Box 7, Folder 25)
      - Population study of Song Sparrow review (Box 7, Folder 26)
      - Song Sparrow abstracts, Song Sparrow II (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Song Sparrow, banding (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Song Sparrow, banding- smmaries and calculations (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - The Cowbird (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Song Sparrow Diary, Apr.-June 1935 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Song Sparrow XVII- driving off other species (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Winter - individual, flocking (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Interpont II (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Song Sparrow, census maps, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Maps, key table to males (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Map, cowbirds (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Genealogical maps, song sparrow territory (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Interpont census maps (Box 8, Folder 13)
      - Song Sparrow, census maps, 1930-1932 (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - Song Sparrow, census maps (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - Census maps, spring and summer, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - Song Sparrow census maps, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 17)
      - Song Sparrow, song plots, census maps, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 18)
      - Song Sparrow, misc., 1930 (Box 8, Folder 19)
      - Song Sparrow II, misc. (Box 8, Folder 20)
      - Song Sparrow, Misc. notes (Box 8, Folder 21)
      - Molting (Box 8, Folder 22)
      - Song Sparrow, nests (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - nest building, incubation (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Song Sparrow banding, new key tables, nestlings distances from home (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Song Sparrow, stages of nesting cycle (re: young out of nest) (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Song Sparrow, success of nests depending on location (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Song Sparrow, voice of female, voice of male, pouncing, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Song Sparrow, roosting (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Song Sparrow, development of song during nest building, etc. (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - 9 songs, answering songs, 1929-1935 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Song Sparrow, awakening songs, 1934-1935 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Awakening songs, other species (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Awakening songs, Jan.-June 1930-1934 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Awakening song, old material (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Awakening song, working sheet and charts (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Awakening, temperature thresholds (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Song Sparrow, song and temperature (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Song Sparrow, song development interpretation (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Song Sparrow, development of song (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - XV, female song (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - XIII or XIV, Song Sparrow, song inherited or learned (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - Song Series, 1929-1932 (Box 9, Folder 21)
      - Uno, song series (Box 9, Folder 22)
      - Song Sparrow, IV, six seasons records of songs (Box 9, Folder 23)
      - Spring, singing record (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Home records and song series, summaries and totals (Box 9, Folder 25)
      - Song Sparrow in 1931, S.S. soul, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 26)
      - Song Sparrow, summaries (Box 9, Folder 27)
      - Survival on Interpont (Box 9, Folder 28)
      - Territory (Box 9, Folder 29)
      - Song Sparrow, young in nest, Uno and Una, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 30)
      - Song Sparrow, young out of nest and Caruso (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Development of Behavior in Precocial and Altricial Birds
      - Original outline (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Notes for chapter I and source material (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Chapter III notes (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Chapter IV notes (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Chapter V notes (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Chapter VI notes (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Chapter VIA notes (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Chapter VIA notes (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Chapter VIB notes (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Chapter VIC notes (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Chapter VII, notes, first draft (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Chapter VIIIa notes (Box 10, Folder 12)
      - Chapter VIIIB (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Chapter VIIIB Virginias (Box 10, Folder 14)
      - Chapter VIIIB (Box 10, Folder 15)
      - Chapter VIIIC notes (Box 10, Folder 16)
      - Chapter IX notes (Box 10, Folder 17)
      - Chapter IX, gulls and terns notes (Box 10, Folder 18)
      - Chapter X notes (Box 10, Folder 19)
      - Chapter XIIB (Box 10, Folder 20)
      - Chapter XIII notes (Box 10, Folder 21)
      - Table of Contents (Box 10, Folder 22)
      - Chapter I (Box 10, Folder 23)
      - Chapter II, practically ready (Box 10, Folder 24)
      - Chapter III (Box 10, Folder 25)
      - Chapter IV (Box 10, Folder 26)
      - Chapter V (Box 10, Folder 27)
      - Chapter VIA (Box 10, Folder 28)
      - Chapter VIB (Box 10, Folder 29)
      - Chapter VIC (Box 10, Folder 30)
      - Chapter VII (Box 10, Folder 31)
      - Chapter VIIIA (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Chapter VIIIB (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Chapter IX (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Chapter X (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Chapter XI (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Chapter XII (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Chapter XIII (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Chapter XIV (prelim. Draft) (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Chapter XIV (second draft) (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - General summary (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Bibliography (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - Species index (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Index for Precocial Birds (Song Sparrow II) Index of Subjects (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Photos (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - Drawings (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Drawings (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - Extra tables (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Development of Behavior in Precocial Birds
      - Chapter I, galleys (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Chapters II & III (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Chapters IV & V (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Chapter VI (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Chapter VII (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Chapter VIII (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - Chapter IX & X (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Chapter XI (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - Chapter XIII & XIV (Box 12, Folder 18)
      - General summary, bibliography (Box 12, Folder 19)
      - Illustrations of book (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Abstracts of books
      - Mating (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Migration (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Population (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Psychology (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Sex (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Song (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Territory (1) (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Territory (2) (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Spring rivalry, territory, weight, longevity, molt, temperature (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Young dominance (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - Behavior (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Abstracts of books: Cuckoo (Box 15, Folder 12)
      - Abstracts of books: ecology, flocking (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - Abstract of behavior: authors (Box 15, Folder 14)
      - Abstracts of behavior, banding, misc. (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - European articles ( 1938 ), golden orioles, hungary seven baby birds (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - European articles co-authored by Konrad Lorenz and Altenberg (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Articles on hares (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Review (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - European relief, American Association of Advancement of Science Bulletin (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Auk abstracts (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Auk articles (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Auk articles (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Articles in different periodicals (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Propaganda, Joost article, 1956-1957 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Migratory behavior in song sparrows (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Red-wing article (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Article "Late Spring in Arkansas" (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous articles from various ornithological publications (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Black and white warbler (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Article, wood pewees (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Various articles from other authors (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Articles, vultures (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Incubation periods III b, notes (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Incubation periods, articles, notes and tables (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Incubation periods notes (Ib) (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Incubation periods notes (articles) (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Incubation period--Renaissance (articles) (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Incubation period, birds of prey (articles) (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Incubation period, ten-day article (articles) (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Incubation periods (articles) (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Incubation periods, general history of ornithology (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - New World incubation periods, historh of recording (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - incubation periods, history, data (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Incubation periods, New World, 1954 (articles) (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Incubation periods/factor influencing (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Articles--nesting success (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - 5 undated papers (Box 14, Folder 1)